Benjamin Franklin Papers Part 12 -- Letters from Franklin 1733-1789 Mss.B.F85inventory12
American Philosophical Society
- Letters from Benjamin Franklin
  - to [F.] Deumié Groc., 1785 February 25; L.S. 6p.; Franklin, Benjamin
    Answer to M. Deumié Groc's favor of Nov. 26th, 1784, also copies of other original papers relating to the affair of the vessel, "I'Aimable Elizabeth," the sale of her cargo in New Foundland and the total loss to her owners.
  - to William Carmichael, 1785 March 22; A.L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin
    Communicated his letter to Messrs. [John] Adams and [Thomas] Jefferson; had several meetings on the Barbary affair. Is daily expecting permission from Congress to return home.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, X, 159; Bigelow, IX, 90; Smyth, IX, 301).
  - to Maréchal de Castries, 1785 May 16; A.L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin
    Received his letter relative to the advance made to Mr. [William] Bingham, Agent of the United States at Martinique. Mr. Bingham has moved to London. Submits to his consideration whether it would not be well to charge the French Minister at London with the demand, as he (Dr. Franklin) is about to depart for America and will not have an opportunity of seeing Mr. Bingham.
    Printed in Works (Smyth, IX, 328).
  - to [Whom it May Concern], 1785 May 19; A. Dr. of L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin
    Certifies that M. [L]air De Lamotte served as one of his Secretaries and conducted himself uniformly with great diligence, exactitude, fidelity and ability. Parts with him because, having resigned his employment, he has now no occasion for his services.
  - to Rev. Mr. Wyvil., 1785 June 10; A.L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin
    Sends the sketch he promised. Perhaps it may be of use to publish something of the kind; for it the power of choosing now in the boroughs continues to be allowed as a right, they may think themselves justifiable in demanding more of it, or in holding back longer, than they would if they find that it begins to be considered as an abuse.
  - to Mme. -----., 1785 July 1; A. Dr. of L. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Are all upset by preparations for leaving. Is very anxious to see her but cannot go to her house as he is suffering from the gout. Invites her to dine with him on Sunday.
  - to [Claudius Crigan, Bishop of Sodor and Man], 1785 July 5; A. Dr. of L. 4p.; Franklin, Benjamin
    Practicability and expediency of establishing a bishop in America.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, X, 202; Bigelow, IX, 140; Smyth, IX, 353).
  - to Charles William Frederick Dumas., 1785 July 5; L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin
    Is about to return to Philadelphia where he will be glad to be of service to him.
  - to [Charles Joseph] Mathon de la Cour., 1785 July 9; Dr. of L. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin
    Accepts with gratitude the title conferred on him by the Academy of Lyons. Will never forget what he owes to the French people and still less to the Academy which has honored him on the eve of his departure from France.
    Printed in Works (Smyth, IX, 362).
  - Memorandum., [1785 July 12]; A. Mem. 2p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Itemized list of improvements and repairs made in M. [Le Ray] de Chaumont's house by Dr. Franklin during his occupancy of it.
  - Memorandum., 1785 July 12; A. Mem. S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Produced the foregoing to M. [Le Ray] de Chaumont in opposition to his demand for reparation to windows, furniture, etc. They agreed to strike a balance and that all should be considered as even on both sider.
  - Memorandum., 1785 July 27; A. Mem. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Send [Gov.] W[illiam] F[ranklin] in London all papers tending to elucidate his (Benjamin Franklin's) title to lands in Nova Scotia, and such agreement as may be necessary form him to sign. He is to convey half of what he may recover to his sister [Mrs. Richard Bache].
  - to William Vernon., 1785 October 14; A. Dr. of L. 6p.; Franklin, Benjamin. Philadelphia
    Account of his son [William Vernon, Jr.,]'s conduct in Paris. His opinion of what seems most necessary to be done respecting him.
  - to Messrs. Sears and Smith., 1785 November 14; A.L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. Philadelphia
    Is surprised they did not receive his reply to theirs of May 18. Encloses a copy of it.
    Printed in Works (Smyth, IX, 475).
  - Remarks Upon the Navigation from New Foundland to New york., 1785 December; A. Diss. S. 2p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    To avoid the gulf stream on one hand, and, on the other, the shoals that lie to the southward of Nantucket and of St. George's Banks. Read before the American Philosophical Society, December 2. 1785.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, VI, 496; Bigelow, IX, 194; Smyth, IX, 405).
  - to [William] Vernon, Jr., [1785.]; A. Dr. of L. 2p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Was informed that he was still embarrassed in his money affairs. Advises him to return to America; can see no necessity of his staying in Paris any longer. Is willing to lend him more money to pay off his debts, on condition that he returns to America.
  - to ----- ------, [1786.]; A. Dr. of L. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Relative to the payment of the National debt and the evacuation of the frontier posts by Great Britain.
  - to John Vaughan, 1828; Lee, Richard Henry
    Not in Hays Calendar Catalogued 8 May 1975. M.D.S.
  - Conversation Between Dr. Franklin and Lord Hillsborough, 1771 January 16; Franklin, Benjamin
    Formerly bd. with 973.3: AC2
  - to Charles Biddle., 1786 November 2; A.L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. Philadelphia
    The report he mentions that his conduct has been disapproved of by him is an infamous falsehood; he has always appeared to him to be an excellent officer, well understanding the duties of his station and indefatigably active in their performance.
    Printed in Works (Smyth, IX, 545).
  - Inventions of John Churchman., 1787 February 14; D. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Certificate by Dr. Franklin that the list of inventions had been submitted to him.
  - to W[illiam] T[emple] Franklin, New York., 1787 April 26; A.L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. Philadelphia
    Found Major [David Salisbury] Frank's note and encloses it; if he cannot get the money immediately, and the Major proposes to pay it shortly, directs him to leave the note with Mr. [Richard] Bache and request him to receive the money for him.
  - to [Francis] Childs., 1787 May 8; L. 3p.; Franklin, Benjamin. Philadelphia
    His paper does not come regularly; is glad to hear, however, that it is well established and is likely to be profitable. Relative to the imperfection in the founts; his grandson [Benjamin Franklin Bache] will cast the sorts for him, as soon as he has taken his degree and got clear from College.
    Printed in Works (Smyth, IX, 580).
  - to [John] Smith., 1787 August 31; L.S. 3p.; Franklin, Benjamin. Philadelphia
    Received his letter requesting a loan of £130 to be repaid if not found due to the estate of his father. Asserts that if he could persuade himself that he really owed the money, he would pay it immediately, but he belives the accounts must have been settled and adjusted. An account of the circumstances which persuade him that he is in no way indebted to his father.
  - to S[amuel] Osgood and A[rthur] Lee., 1787 August 31; A. Dr. of L. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. Philadelphia
    Respecting the accounts of Mr. [John] Ross supposed to be in his hands. Made a search but could not find them. Thinks they were delivered with the other public documents to Tho[ma]s Barclay. Will order his grandson, who is now in Albany, to make a more careful search for them when he returns. Will deliver them should they be found.
    Printed in Works (Smyth, IX, 606).
  - Instructions to the Commander of the Militia and to the Commissioners, in Relation to the Riot in Luzerne Country, Pa., [1787 October ?]; A. Mem. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
  - to J[ohn] Ross., 1788 January 21; Dr. of L. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. Philadelphia
    Is again called upon by the Board of Treasury for the vouchers to Ross's accounts with Congress, which were produced to Messrs. [Samuel] Wharton and [Edward] Bancroft. Much of this transaction took place as long ago as 1779, and has escaped his memory and therefore requests to be informed with what he knows concerning it, and particularly in regard to the whereabouts of the vouchers; cannot find them among his papers.
    Printed in Works (Smyth, IX, 630).
  - to Samuel Osgood and Walter Livingston., 1788 January 31; A. Dr. of L.S. 2p.; Franklin, Benjamin. Philadelphia
    Cannot find the vouchers of Mr. [John] Ross's accounts, deposited with him when in France. When he left France be ordered all papers relating to public affairs and everything deposited with him as Consul, to be put in Mr. [Thomas] Barclay's hands. Is of the opinion that the vouchers are among those papers. Mr. Ross writes that he has an authenticated copy which he is ready to produce, if necessary, but thinks that some of the copies that were made still exist.
    Printed in Works (Smyth, IX, 631).
  - to J. Ingenhousz., 1788 February 11; A.L.S. 4p.; Franklin, Benjamin. Philadelphia
    His health. The horror and cost of wars. Is sorry for the losses he met with in his attempt to make profit by commerce in America. Decline of Continental money, and the cause thereof. Relative to his trouble with Mr. [Samuel] Wharton.
    Printed in Works (in part, Sparks, X, 333; Bigelow, IX, 454; in full, Smyth, IX, 633).
  - to ----- -----, 1788 February 17; A. Dr. of L. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. Philadelphia
    Received and read the letter she sent him last summer.
  - to [Mathew Carey]., 1788 June 10; A. Dr. of L. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. Philadelphia
    The periodical compilation he proposes seems to be a novel idea. Such a work, if well executed, recommends itself; and if it is not well executed, it will not be helped by any other recommendation. Incloses a note of the value of provisions 34 years ago in Philadelphia and Boston, which he thinks might be proper to be preserved in his works.
    Printed in Works (Smyth, IX, 660).
  - to J[ohn] Jay., 1788 June 27; A.L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. Philadelphia
    In looking over his papers he found a copy of a certificate of Com. [John Paul] Jones in favor of John Jackson. Wishes to be informed whether anything has been done for Jackson, in consequence of Jones's promise. Sends him two papers relative to the services done the United States by Mr. [Andrew] Limozin of Havre and M. Milliet of Lisbon, for his consideration and to be disposed of as he should think proper.
    Printed in Works (Smyth, IX, 662).
  - to [Joseph] Elam., 1788 November 10; A.L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. Philadelphia
    Declines the arbitration of a sectarian squabble. His advice to them.
    Printed in Works (Bigelow, X, 18; Smyth, IX, 680).
  - to [Philip] Kinsey., 1789 May 25; A. Dr. of L. in 3d P.; Franklin, Benjamin. Philadelphia
    Some mistake in the supposition that the box [containing sundry geometrical solid bodies] was ever lent to him. His memory still pretty good and it affords not the least trace of any such transaction.
  - List of Learned Societies of which Benjamin Franklin was a Member., [1789.]; A. Mem. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
  - Ledger A and B, 1730-1740 July; 2 Vols. Folio.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
  - Leger D., 1739-1748; 2 Vols. Folio.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
  - Receipt Book., 1742-1764; I vol. Small 4to.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
  - Post-Office Book., 1748-1752; I Vol. Folio.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
  - Account of Expenses of Benjamin Franklin's Voyage to England., 1757; I Vol. Small 4to.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
  - Memorandum Book., 1757 April to 1776 October; I Vol. Folio.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
  - Journal Kept During his Residence in London., 1764-1774; I vol. 4to.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
  - Account of the Money Received from the Commissioners of the United States for their use., 1777; I vol. 4to.; Franklin, Benjamin. Paris
  - to Arra Shoy., A. Dr. of Diss. 2p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    A poem on Mareashine. The relative advantages of New York and Pennsylvania for settlers.
  - to Mme. Brillon., A.L. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    The real cause for his leaving her house so soon was that he had been up carly that day, had worked hard, had dined in Paris and felt rather sleepy after she had retired to the garden. Thought it more seemly to take his leave early in the evening and go home. She must, therefore, forgive him and not be angry over little things.
  - to Mme. Brillon, 1p.; A.L. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Autograph Draft of same. (XLVI(i), 48)
    Printed in Putnam's Monthly, Dec., 1906, 314.
  - to Mme. Brillon., A. Dr. of L. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Believes that there are many pleasures in this world, as well as pains, and is glad to live. Providence should not be blamed; many of our duties are by Nature made pleasures.
    Printed in Putnam's Monthly, Dec., 1906, 316.
  - to The Ship "Capricieuse.", Dr. of D. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
  - to [William] Caslon., A. Mem. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Order for types and paper.
  - to Le Ray de Chaumont., A.N. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Requests the loan of his piano.
  - Passport for Irish Settlers., A. Dr. of D.S. 3p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    On board the brigantine "Eliizabeth." Captain William Stewart commanding.
  - to [The Comtesse de Golowsin], [before 1781 February 1]; A. Dr. of N. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    To his faithful interpreter of German letters.
  - to Dr. Ingen Housz., A. Dr. of D.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
  - to [Jean Baptiste] Le Roy., 1778 After Dec.18; A. Dr. of N. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Asking for the address of the Governor of San Domingo.
  - to Dr. [Charles?] Morton., A. Dr. of L. in 3d P. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Sends him the book on education said to be written by Mr. Walker. An account of the author may be found in the Athenae Oxoniensis.
  - to The Portuguese Vessel "La Nostra Signora.", Dr. of D. 2p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
  - to Robert Pasley and Family., Dr. of D. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
  - to The Printer., A. Dr. of L. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Definition of British newspapers. Like Ambassadors, they are sent abroad to lie.
  - to Mme. Helvetus, [1778?]; N. 1p.; Torgot
    Cannot see her this evening and desires to know if the dinner with M. De La Fay will take place to-morrow.
  - Memorandum., [Ca. 1760]; A. Mem. 1P.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    An hypothetical case to ascertain the custom of merchants in reference to commissions on a commercial transaction.
  - Money Advanced by Different Persons to American Prisoners., [1778; Mem. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
  - A Turkish Apologue., A. Dr. of Diss. 3p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
  - Memoranda., A. Dr. 6p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Miscellaneous.
    - Plan of Franklin Court property in Philadelphia, 1765; 1 map, 2 copies, 37.1 x 23.5 cm
      Other Finding Aids note
      Realms of Gold, 15 (3) and 15 (4).
  - [Invitation for a Party ?], [1778 ?]; A. Mem. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
  - Statement of Account with the Estate of James Parker., [1763-1772.]; Mem. 2p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
  - Post-Office Accounts., [1741-1773.]; Mem. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
  - Trial Balance., 1771 February 28; Mem. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
  - Trial Balance., [1775] May 31; Mem. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
  - Statement of Account with Jona[than] Williams., 1776 February 29; Mem. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. Worcester
  - Statement of Account with William Hodgson., 1782 July 26; Mem. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. London
  - Statement of Account with William Hodgson., 1783 October 24; Mem. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. London
  - Bills and Business Memoranda., 1778/9 Jan. 25; 1731-33; 1734; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
  - Bill of Exchange., 1782 December 20; A. Dr. of D. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin
    Drawn on Robert Morris, Superintendent of Finance, Philadelphia.
  - The Bank [of North America]., D.S. 9p.; Franklin, Benjamin. Philadelphia
    Cheques from May 5, 1787, to July 21, 1788. Philadelphia.
  - Bond to Jean de Neufville and Fils., 1781; Mem. 7p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Form of bond to be signed on receiving 200,000 florins from Jean de Neufville and Fils, of Amsterdam, as part of the loan of 2,000,000 florins authorized by Congress and floated by them. Another form to be signed by Congress.
  - Form of Bond to be Issued by the American Commissioners at Paris., Dr. of D. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    For money loaned, with interest coupons attached.
  - Form of Bond to be Issued by the American Commissioners at Paris., D. 2p.; Dr. of D. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    (Printed proof.)
  - Blank form of Book for Entry of Bills Receivable., Dr. of Mem. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
  - Blank form of Book for Entry of Bills Payable., Dr. of Mem. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
  - Blank Bond of Indemnity., A. Dr. of D. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    To Benjamin Franklin for payment of Continental bill of exchange which had not been endorsed.
  - Receipt for Papers in Connection with Prizes Brought Into Port., Printed. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
  - Amount of Loan Office Bills Accepted by Benjamin Franklin., Mem. 3p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
  - Summary of Amount of Bills in Dollars and Livres., Mem. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
  - List of Bills of Exchange Not Accepted., [1780 Aug.]; Mem. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
  - Note Payable to the President of the Continental Congress for Money Received from Benjamin Franklin., Printed forms. 2p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Passy Inprint.
  - Note Given by Prisoners in England for Money Advanced to Assist in Returning to the United States., Printed form. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Accession Note
    Deaccessioned in 1972, sold as duplicate
  - Bond Given by Commander of Letter of Marque Ship., Printed form 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
  - Written and Printed Blank Forms of Bonds for Persons Taking out Letters of Marque and Reprisal., D. 7p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790